Guide to the Theresa Helburn Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Theresa Helburn papers
1887-1992
1920-1958
YCAL MSS 864
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.5
(13 boxes) + 1 broadside.
The Theresa Helburn Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, financial documents, writings, photographs, scrapbooks and memorabilia documenting her career as a writer and theatrical director and administrator for the Theatre Guild and other theaters.
Helburn, Theresa, 1887-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret (Mrs. Eric) Kocher and other Kocher family members, 1966-2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated material: Theatre Guild Archive (YCAL MSS 436). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Theresa Helburn (1887-1959)
Theresa Helburn was born in New York City in 1887, graduated from Bryn Mawr College in 1908, and had an early career as a writer of essays, poetry, and plays, and as a theatre critic for the The Nation. In 1919, she joined the Theatre Guild in New York City as a play reader. Within a few years she was co-administrative director with Lawrence Langner. As a writer, critic, director, and administrator, Theresa Helburn was a major force in the development of twentieth-century American theatre. She was married to the writer and teacher John Baker Opdycke (Oliver to his friends) from 1921 until his death in 1958. Helburn died in 1959.
Scope and Contents
The Theresa Helburn Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, financial documents, writings, photographs, scrapbooks and memorabilia documenting her career as a writer and theatrical director and administrator for the Theatre Guild and other theatres.
The correspondence in the collection is predominately personal, and includes letters from Carlotta O'Neill describing her husband's illness, a typed copy of an exchange between Helburn and George Bernard Shaw regarding her work in the film industry, and a letter from Shaw's assistant, Blanche Patch, describing the playwright's death. Helburn's diaries and date books include short entries about her meetings, travel, and social events, and often contain references to her health and the weather. Financial documents provide information regarding not only her daily personal expenses, but her own financial investment in Theatre Guild productions as well as in stocks and oil. Helburn's writing career is documented by early notes and story ideas, drafts and published versions of articles and presentations, poetry, and autobiographical essays, including those published in The Nation. Her work in, and opinions about, the film industry are described in drafts of articles and in the film story ideas, synopses, and comments that Helburn either wrote or reviewed while working in Hollywood at Columbia Pictures in mid-1930s.
While there is one file of material relating to Helburn's autobiography (which was completed and published after her death), the most substantial biographical information regarding her professional life is found in the scrapbooks that Helburn maintained from 1919 to 1950. Newspaper and magazine clippings of articles by and about Helburn, performance programs from the plays she wrote and/or directed, along with other miscellaneous ephemera, illuminate her many activities in the world of literature, theatre, and film. The papers also include photographs of family members, friends and colleagues, as well as candid and portrait photographs of Helburn. Material post-dating Helburn's death, including condolence letters, obituaries, and records pertaining to her estate, was added by family members.
Arrangement
The Papers are organized in three groupings: I. Pre-2010 Acquisitions,1903-1958. II. Material Formerly Part of the Theatre Guild Archive, 1918-1958. III. 2010 Acquisitions, 1887-1992.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Theater -- United States; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States; Photographs; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States -- 20th Century; Helburn, Theresa, 1887-1959; Opdycke, John B. (John Baker), 1878-1956; Theatre Guild
- Pre-2010 Accessions, 1903-1958; 1; 4.33; (6 boxes)
  - Personal Files, 1922-1960
    Arrangement
    The Personal Files are organized into four subcategories: Correspondence, Diaries, Financial Records, and Photographs
    - Correspondence
      - "A" - "W" and unidentified, 1938-58, undated (Box 1)
      - Bryn Mawr College, 1948 (Box 1)
      - Denenholz, Reginald, 1952-53 (Box 1)
      - O'Neill, Carlotta Monterey, 1948-53, undated (Box 1)
      - Shaw, George Bernard, 1935, 1950 (Box 1)
      - Woollcott, Alexander, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Christmas cards, 1953, undated (Box 1)
      - Postcards, 1953-58, undated (Box 1)
      - Third Party, 1922-1960 (Box 1)
      - Notes and invitations containing directions to friends' homes, H-S, unidentified, undated (Box 1)
    - Diaries, [1910], 1928-1954; 12 (Box 1)
    - Financial records
      - Check registers
        - Bankers Trust Company, 1937-1946; 5 (Box 1)
        - Chase National Bank, 1943-1947 (Box 1)
        - Chemical Bank and Trust, 1944-1946 (Box 2)
        - Fifth Avenue Bank of New York, 1940-1951; 4 (Box 2)
        - Unidentified bank, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
      - Statements and deposit slips from various banks, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
      - Investment records
        - A. W. Smith & Co., 1945-1950 (Box 2)
        - Oil lease, 1949 (Box 2)
        - Stock records, 1938-1950 (Box 2)
        - Texmass Petroleum Company, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Photograph of Helburn and tintype of unidentified boy, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1903-1956
    The Writings are arranged alphabetically within three subcategories: Articles, Poetry, and Presentations; Film Story Ideas, Treatments, Synopses, and Comments; and Notes
    - Articles, poetry, and presentations
      - Autobiographical essays, drafts, typescript and holograph, corrected, 1935, undated (Box 2)
      - "The Aviator," a poem published in The Bellman, Volume XX, number 500, 1916 Feb 12 (Box 2)
      - "Critics for Sunday Only," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - "Drama," columns from The Nation, 1919 January 4 - May 24; 2 (Box 2)
      - "Exerpts from Remarks Delivered at the Dinner of the Yale Drama Alumni, Yale Club, June 4, 1944" draft typescript, corrected (Box 2)
      - "From One Guild to Another," published version in Opera News, 1941 February 24 (Box 2)
      - "Mother," published version of poem clipped by the Romeike press clipping bureau from numerous U.S. newspapers, 1932 May 7, 8 (Box 2)
      - "On Experiment," draft, typescript carbon, 1946 Jul 29 and published version from the The New York Times 1946 Aug 4 (Box 2)
      - "O'Neill: an Impression," published version published in The Saturday Review of Literature, 1936 November 21 (Box 2)
      - "Some Random Musings on Bright College Years," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2)
      - ["The Theatre, Bloody but Unbowed,"] drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected (published in the North American Review Summer 1937) (Box 2)
      - "Theatre Versus Pictures," draft, typescript, and published version from the Journal of the American Association of University Women 1936 January; accompanied by notes and typescript drafts of essays comparing theatre and film (Box 2)
      - "To You," printed version of poem published in The Poetry Journal, 1917 March (Box 2)
      - "What's in a Title?," printed version, published in Leblang's Theatre Bulletin, 1948 April (Box 2)
    - Film story ideas, treatments, synopses, and comments
      Scope and Contents
      Consist of drafts, typescript, some corrected and/or annotated.
      - " The Ambassadors by Henry James", undated (Box 2)
      - "'Annette and Sylvie,' Volume I of The Soul Enchanted by Romain Rolland", 1935 March 22 (Box 2)
      - " Chartreuse de Parme [by] Stendahl", 1935 April 5 (Box 2)
      - "The Crystal Goblet", 1935 April 5 (Box 2)
      - "The Disappearance of Delight", undated (Box 2)
      - "Fair Ellen", 1935; 2 (Box 2)
      - " The Golden Bowl by Henry James", undated (Box 2)
      - " The Gypsy Queen of Paris by R. McNair Wilson", undated (Box 2)
      - "The Insane Root", undated (Box 2)
      - "The Lesser Evil", undated (Box 2)
      - "Machinale", undated (Box 2)
      - "'Maid of Honor,' new treatment by Zoe Akins", 1935 June 29 (Box 2)
      - "The Naked Man", undated (Box 2)
      - Transcript of text of letter from S. K. Lauren to Harry Cohn regarding censorship issues in adapting One Night in June by Somerset Maugham for the screen, undated (Box 2)
      - " The Pleasure of Honesty by Luigi Pirandello", undated (Box 2)
      - "The Pomeroy Baby," draft, typescript carbon, accompanied by "The Biltmore Baby", undated (Box 2)
      - " The Red and the Black [by] Stendahl", 1935 April 4 (Box 2)
      - "Rich Girl, Poor Girl", undated (Box 2)
      - "Roger Gordon", undated (Box 2)
      - Untitled story ideas, 1935 March (Box 2)
      - Untitled treatment, undated (Box 2)
    - Notes, 1903, 1916, 1956, undated; 4 (Box 2)
      Includes holograph notes and quotations; notes for plays and story ideas; and outlines for courses on plays and modern poetry, accompanied by an annotated 1916 program of lectures at The Manor Club
  - Scrapbooks and Memorabilia, 1903-1958
    Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically; Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Scrapbooks
      - 1911-1923 (Box 3)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 3)
      - 1929-1931 (Box 3)
      - 1932-1934 (Box 3)
      - 1935-1937 (Box 3)
      - 1934-1941 (Box 4)
      - 1942-1948 (Box 4)
      - 1949-1950
      - 1951-1952 (Box 4)
      - "New York Reviews of the Importance of Being Earnest for Theresa Helburn", 1947
      - Theatre Guild twenty-fifth anniversary scrapbook, 1944
    - Memorabilia
      - American National Theatre and Academy (ANTA)
        - Program for "ANTA Album" production at the Ziegfeld Theatre, 1951 May 6 (Box 4)
        - Chapter One, two issues of the newsletter of the Greater New York Chapter of ANTA, 1957, April, May (Box 4)
      - American Shakespeare Festival programs, 1957, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Bryn Mawr
        - Diploma, 1908
        - "The Blue Heron," 50th reunion booklet, 1958 (Box 4)
      - Kidnapped performance program, undated (Box 4)
      - Opdycke, John Baker: miscellaneous notes, clippings, and ephemera, 1910-1956 (Box 4)
      - Theatre Guild
        - Financial documents from productions of Bonds of Interest and He Who Gets Slapped, 1919, 1946 (Box 4)
        - The History of the Theatre Guild, 1919-1934 (Box 4)
        - The History of the Theatre Guild, 1919-1937 (Box 4)
        - The Story of the Theatre Guild, 1919-1947; with typescript notes laid in (Box 4)
        - Theatre Guild Bulletin [an occasional newsletter], 1946, undated (Box 4)
        - "The Theater [sic] Guild," Congressional Record reprint, 1946 (Box 4)
        - Souvenir program for Mary of Scotland, [1933] (Box 4)
        - Program for "The Theatre Guild on the Air" production of Ned McCobb's Daughter, produced by United States Steel on WJZ and stations of the American Broadcasting Company, 1945 December 9 (Box 4)
        - Page from program for Arms and the Girl, [1950] (Box 4)
        - " Oklahoma! the first ten years, a round-up improvised by Warren Caro and Reginald Denenholz...at the Tenth Birthday Party," mimeograph songbook, 1953 Mar 31 (Box 4)
        - Actors' Fund of America salute to the Theatre Guild's Fortieth Season, program/menu, 1958 May 11 (Box 4)
        - " Oklahoma! ," color photographic essay published in Coronet magazine, 1944 June (Box 4)
        - "Broadway Loves Their Brand of Lunacy," published in Magazine Digest, 1945 April (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings, 1925-1958; 2 (Box 4)
      - Westport Country Playhouse programs, 1953, 1957 July 22-September 2 (Box 4)
        Productions include What About Maisie?, The Saturday Night Kid, With Respect to Joey, Janus, Fever for Life, Showtime, Back to Methuselah, and The Minotaur
      - Miscellaneous clippings, 1920-1950; 2 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous publications
        - "Danger Ahead: Asia," by William Randolph Hearst, Jr., reprint from the New York Journal American, [1956] (Box 4)
        - "Le Dédale" by Paul Hervieu, published as a supplement to L'Illustration, 1903 December 26 (Box 4)
        - That Freedom May Not Perish..., pamphlet published by The International Rescue Committee's Program in Support of the Hungarian Freedom Fighters, [1957?] (Box 4)
        - Mid-winter book supplement of The Nation, 1921 February 9 (Box 4)
        - The North American Review issue, Vol. 243, number 1, 1937 Spring (Box 4)
        - Snappy Stories issue, Vol. X, number 1, 1921 July 25 (Box 4)
        - Stage Pictorial issue, Vol. 3, number 5, 1946 July (Box 4)
        - Toward Arab-Israeli Conciliation: Memorandum on the Eastern Mediterranean, pamphlet published by the Institute for Mediterranean Affairs, 1958 (Box 4)
        - Vedanta Society brochures: What is Vedanta? and Why a Hindu is a Vegetarian, 1900, undated (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1929-1947, undated (Box 4)
  - Oversize
    - Scrapbooks (Box 5 (Oversize))
    - Helburn's Bryn Mawr diploma, 1908 (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Opdycke ephemera (Box 6 (Oversize))
- Materials Formerly Part of the Theatre Guild Archive, 1918-1957; 2; 1; (1 box)
  - Correspondence
    - Craig, Edward Gordon, 1918-1919 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence regarding Helburn plays, 1927-1956; 3 (Box 7)
      Includes correspondence, production materials and press clippings relating to Crysalis
    - Invitations to miscellaneous events, 1931-1954 (Box 7)
  - Writings
    - Plays
      - "A Hero is Born", 1937; 2 (Box 7)
      - "Other Lives", undated (Box 7)
    - Articles, 4 (Box 7)
      Includes writings by Helburn published in Bryn Mawr College literary magazines, and articles on Philip Moeller, and articles published in The New Republic.
    - Talks and presentations, 1944-1953; 2 (Box 7)
    - Interview transcripts and scripts, 1940, 1952, undated (Box 7)
    - Autobiographical sketches, undated (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs of Helburn as Queen Elizabeth, 1944 (Box 7)
  - Printed material
    - Call Bureau Classification, "property of Columbia Pictures Corporation", [1934?] (Box 7)
    - Theatre Incorporated Has the Honor to Present The Old Vic Theatre Company ..., by Edward Choate and John F. Matthews, 1946 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets and brochures, 1949-1957, undated (Box 7)
- 2010 Acquisitions, 1887-1992; 3; 3.17; (5 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1902-1958; 13 (Box 8)
    - Martin, Mary and Richard Halliday, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Munson, Ona, 1950-1955 (Box 8)
    - Shaw, Bernard, 1920-1935 (Box 8)
      Consists of typed transcriptions of letters to Helburn from Shaw.
    - Yale University Library, 1957-1962 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence regarding Theresa Helburn's death and estate, 1959-1987; 5 (Box 8)
    Includes letters of condolence, correspondence with attorney's and financial advisors and family members.
  - Photographs, 1887-1943, undated; 7 (Box 8)
    Includes family photographs, portraits photographs of Helburn and John Opdycke, and friends and colleagues.
  - Handwriting analysis, 1917 (Box 8)
  - Writings
    - Poetry, undated (Box 8)
    - Talks and lectures, circa 1950s (Box 8)
    - Notes for autobiographical sketches, undated (Box 8)
    - Clippings, 1932, 1937 (Box 8)
      Includes clippings of the poem, "Mother" from a clipping service, and an issue of North American Review containing an article by Helburn.
  - Yearly appointment books and diaries, 1910-1958, undated; 15 (Box 9)
  - European trip diary, 1926 July-August (Box 9)
  - Small scrapbook of poems by various authors clipped from newspapers, undated (Box 9)
  - Theatre Guild records
    - Memoranda, 1955 (Box 10)
    - Oklahoma!, 1943-1953, undated (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1955-1956, undated (Box 10)
    - Appraisals of Theatre Guild records, 1955 (Box 10)
  - Honorary degrees
    - Columbia University, 1954 (Box 10)
    - Franklin and Marshall College, 1952; 2 (Box 10)
      Includes degrees of Theresa Helburn and John Opdycke.
  - Obituary notices, 1956, 1959; 2 (Box 10)
    Includes press clippings and other obituaries for Theresa Helburn and John Opdycke.
  - Printed material, 3 (Box 10)
    Includes a small volume of the New Testament and Settings and Costumes of the Modern Stage by Theodore Komisarjevsky and Lee Simonson inscribed to Helburn from Simonson.
  - Embroidered cat, "Diamond", undated (Box 10)
  - Oversize
    - Photographs, undated; 5 (Box 11)
    - Small drawings, 1965, undated; 2 (Box 11)
    - Honorary degrees and awards, 1945-1992; 2 (Box 12)
    - Photographs, undated; 2 (Box 12)
    - Printed reproductions of film posters, undated; 2 (Box 12)
    - Drawings, undated; 5 (Box 12)
      Includes a color set design drawing for Oklahoma!, and a charcoal drawing of Theresa Helburn.
    - Photographs of Theresa Helburn, undated; 2 (Box 13)
    - Caricature of Theresa Helburn, 1953 (Box 13)
    - Charcoal portrait of Theresa Helburn, 1940 (Box 14 (Broadside))